Guide to the Delta Sigma Phi Fraternity. Alpha Epsilon Chapter Records, 1920-1972
University Archives Duke University Durham, N.C., USA
Delta Sigma Phi Fraternity. Alpha Epsilon Chapter records 1920-1972
University Archives, Duke University
Delta Sigma Phi Fraternity. Alpha Epsilon Chapter (Duke University)
1 Linear Feet 1000 Items
The Alpha Epsilon chapter of Delta Sigma Phi was established at Duke University in 1920.
Contains the records of the Alpha Epsilon chapter of the Delta Sigma Phi fraternity, a social fraternity for men at Duke University. Types of materials include correspondence, financial summaries, amendments to bylaws, meeting notes, minutes, and printed material. Major subjects include student life at Duke University, hazing, rush, chapter establishment, and governance. Materials range in date from 1920 to 1972.
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
Researchers must register and agree to copyright and privacy laws before using this collection.
In accordance with the Family Education Rights and Privacy Act of 1974 as amended, Duke University permits students to inspect their education records and limits the disclosure of personally identifiable information from education records.
In off-site storage; 48 hours advance notice is required for use.
Provenance
The Delta Sigma Phi Fraternity. Alpha Epsilon Chapter Records were received by the University Archives as a transfer in 1975.
Historical Note
From http://deltasig.org/about/index.html
Late in 1899, a handful of undergraduate men began meeting between classes at City College of New York in Manhattan, N.Y. Some of the men had known one another before they graduated from the New York public school system, and they had wanted to continue their friendships at City College. The obvious solution was to join a fraternity, but this group of friends was an affiliation of Jews and Christians. At the time, entry to all-Jewish and all-Christian fraternities was barred to individuals and groups that mixed religions. Based on the principle of universal brotherhood, the men founded Delta Sigma Phi on December 10, 1899.
Delta Sigma Phi was incorporated in New York City on December 2, 1902. The incorporation papers stated objectives of disseminating "principles of friendship and brotherhood among college men, without respect to race or creed." The purpose of the fraternity was "to fulfill the desire of serious young college men for a fellowship and brotherhood, as near a practical working ideal as possible not fettered with too many traditional prejudices and artificial standards of membership, and accompanied by a clean, pure, and honorable chapter home life." The fraternity is headquartered in Indianapolis, Indiana.
The Alpha Epsilon chapter of Delta Sigma Phi was chartered at Duke University in 1920. Early meetings (1920-1921) held discussions of fraternity jewelry, pledging, installing officers, recruiting new members from prep schools, purchasing furniture and draperies, and planning initiations. In 1920, the chapter adopted Zeta Tau Alpha as their sister fraternity. As of 2006, the members of the Alpha Epsilon live on-campus at Kilgo Quad and are governed by the Interfraternity Council at Duke University. The Alpha Epsilon chapter is currently active.
Collection Overview
Contains correspondence, financial summaries, amendments to bylaws, meeting notes, minutes, and printed material pertaining to the Alpha Epsilon chapter of Delta Sigma Phi at Duke University from 1920-1972. One folder is restricted.
Subject Headings
These are searchable subject entries for this collection. Performing a search on these subjects in the Duke University Libraries online catalog will bring up other related research materials.
College Students -- Alcohol Use -- North Carolina -- Durham
Delta Sigma Phi Fraternity
Duke University
Duke University -- Societies, etc
Duke University -- Students -- Societies, etc
Greek letter societies
Greek letter societies -- North Carolina -- Durham
Hazing
Initiations (into trades, societies, etc.)
Duke University Archives Photograph Collection
Duke University Archives
Fraternities and Sororities Collection, 1931-2001
Duke University Archives
Interfraternity Council Records, 1947-2001
Duke University Archives
Bibliography
Baldwin, Steven L. and Susan Coon Final Report. Office of Student Affairs. Task Force on Greek Life., 1994
Duke University. Interfraternity Council. Fraternity Life at Duke, 1947-1975 [serial]
Contents of Collection
- General Administration Materials,1954-1970
  Contains correspondence, amendments, a housing contract, general financial statements, disciplinary fines levied, letter of expulsion, and pledge materials. The letter of expulsion is restricted. Ordered alphabetically.
  - Correspondence, 1961 (Box 1)
  - Bylaw amendments, 1969-1970
  - Financial, 1950-1951
  - Housing contract, 1960
  - Interfraternity Council, disciplinary actions, 1961
  - Loans and scholarships, ca. 1956
  - Member expulsion, 1960 RESTRICTED
  - Pledge materials, 1954, 1958
- Meetings, 1920-1974
  Contains meeting notes from Alpha Epsilon chapter meetings from 1920-1974 and one folder of Interfraternity Council meeting notes. Ordered by date.
  - Interfraternity Council, Council of Presidents, meeting notes, 1963-1964 (Box 1)
  - Minutes, 1920-1925
  - Minutes, 1928-1931
  - Minutes, 1931-1936
  - Minutes, 1936-1943
  - Minutes, 1944-April 1950 (Box 2)
  - Minutes, May 1950-May 1951
  - Minutes, September 1950-June 1951
  - Minutes, 1953-1956
  - Minutes, 1973-1974
- Printed Material, 1956-1972
  Contains material produced by the Alpha Epsilon chapter, the Delta Sigma Phi headquarters, and Duke University. The Alpha Epsilonian is produced by the Dule university chapter. Ordered alphabetically by title.
  - Alpha Epsilonian, 1956-1963 (Box 2)
  - Alumni Express, 1972
  - The Delta Sigma Phi Fraternity: Notes from International, 1961
  - Float and Decoration Manual, 1962
  - Fraternity Life at Duke University, 1955-1966, published in 1964
  - The Gordian Knot, 1957
  - Member Handbook, 1968
  - Open Relations, 1965
  - Tables of Chapter Standings, 1968-1969